In this part of the lesson I want to show you how each of the five parts of our
في هذا الجزء من الدرس، أريد أن أوضح لكم كيف يتلاءم كل جزء من الأجزاء الخمسة من
MBA conceptual framework fit into the actual management of a business.
الإطار المفاهيمي لماجستير إدارة الأعمال مع الإدارة الفعلية للأعمال التجارية.
And I wanna do this by literally taking you from the ground up to the catbird seat
وأريد أن أفعل هذا بأخذك حرفياً من الألف إلى الياء إلى مقعد القطة
of one of the top corporations in the world hypothetically of course.
لإحدى الشركات الكبرى في العالم بشكل افتراضي بالطبع.
Suppose then you are a young Bill Gates with a hot piece of software.
لنفترض أنك شاب بيل غيتس مع قطعة ساخنة من البرمجيات.
Or, better yet, a young Steve Jobs with an even hotter piece of software.
أو، والأفضل من ذلك، شاب ستيف جوبز مع قطعة أكثر سخونة من البرمجيات.
By using this software or hardware, you and
باستخدام هذا البرنامج أو الأجهزة، أنت
your schoolmates have come up with what you believe is the next killer application
وزملائك في المدرسة قد توصلوا إلى ما تعتقد أنه التطبيق القاتل القادم
in the world of high technology.
في عالم التكنولوجيا العالية.
And this killer app, which you have already patented is so
وهذا التطبيق القاتل، الذي كنت قد حصلت بالفعل على براءة اختراع هو
astonishing that you, well you fill in the blank here because I've got no idea.
مدهش جدا أنك، حسنا ملء الفراغ هنا لأنني لم يكن لدي أي فكرة.
>> At any rate, if you are going to develop this product properly,
>> على أي حال، إذا كنت تنوي تطوير هذا المنتج بشكل صحيح،
the first step you will want to take is to create a business plan.
فإن الخطوة الأولى التي تريد اتخاذها هي إنشاء خطة عمل.
As we learn from Professor Archy, such a plan will precisely define your
وكما نتعلم من البروفيسور آرتشي، فإن هذه الخطة سوف تحدد بدقة
business and identify goals and include such financial accounting tools such
عملك وتحدد الأهداف وتتضمن أدوات المحاسبة المالية
as a pro-forma balance sheet, income statement, and cash flow analysis.
مثل الميزانية العمومية الأولية، وبيان الدخل، وتحليل التدفق النقدي.
This plan will also describe what service or product your business will reach and
ستصف هذه الخطة أيضًا الخدمة أو المنتج الذي ستصل إليه شركتك
what needs in the marketplace it will fill, as well as who your potential
وما هي الاحتياجات في السوق التي ستملأها، وكذلك من
customers are, how you will reach them and why they will purchase it from you.
هم عملاؤك المحتملين، وكيف ستصل إليهم ولماذا سيشتريه منك.
Armed with such a business plan, you and your partners can go about the business
مع هذه الخطة التجارية، يمكنك أنت وشركائك الذهاب إلى العمل في
of trying to raise enough venture capital to get the project up and running.
محاولة لجمع ما يكفي من رأس المال الاستثماري للحصول على المشروع وتشغيله.
Now if your company is successful, you will constantly be raising additional
الآن إذا كانت شركتك ناجحة، سوف تقوم باستمرار بجمع
funds to build new facilities, modernize old ones and
أموال إضافية لبناء مرافق جديدة، وتحديث المرافق القديمة
maybe even acquire some of your rivals to consolidate your position in the industry.
وربما حتى الحصول على بعض من منافسيك لتعزيز وضعك في هذه الصناعة.
All of this will take money and it will be your corporate finance team
كل هذا سوف يستغرق المال وسيكون فريق تمويل الشركات الخاص بك هو
that will help you determine whether you will finance growth by issuing stock or
الذي سيساعدك على تحديد ما إذا كنت ستمول النمو عن طريق إصدار الأسهم أو
bonds or drawing on retained earnings.
السندات أو السحب على الأرباح المحتجزة.
Or, most realistically, using some optimal combination
أو، على نحو أكثر واقعية، استخدام مزيج أمثل
of all three of these forms of so called capital financing.
من هذه الأشكال الثلاثة من ما يسمى بتمويل رأس المال.
Assuming all goes well with this fundraising phase of the business, and
بافتراض أن كل شيء يسير على ما يرام مع مرحلة جمع التبرعات هذه من الأعمال،
that you have enough capital to get your venture off the ground,
وأن لديك رأس المال الكافي لإخراج مشروعك
here are just some of the questions you will be asking your other teams of
من الأرض، فإليك بعض الأسئلة التي ستطرحها على فرقك الأخرى من
MBA equipped experts that you necessarily will assemble to help your company.
الخبراء المجهزين بماجستير إدارة الأعمال الذين ستقوم بتجميعها بالضرورة لمساعدة شركتك.
For starters, even if your product seems like a sure winner, you may still want
بالنسبة للمبتدئين، حتى إذا كان منتجك يبدو فائزًا مؤكدًا، فقد لا تزال تريد من
your management strategy team to examine questions such as these.
فريق استراتيجية الإدارة أن يفحص أسئلة مثل هذه.
Should you even enter the market?
هل يجب عليك حتى دخول السوق؟
And, is there room for another competitor?
و، هل هناك مجال لمنافس آخر؟
Perhaps not.
ربما لا
Are there rivals out there who could bury you with deep financial pockets,
هل هناك منافسين في الخارج يمكن أن يدفنك مع جيوب مالية عميقة،
reputational capital, and established marketing and distribution chains?
رأس المال السمعة، وإنشاء سلاسل التسويق والتوزيع؟
Perhaps so.
ربما ذلك.
If you get the green light from your strategy team and enter the market
إذا حصلت على الضوء الأخضر من فريق الاستراتيجية الخاص بك ودخلت السوق
you will also want to know which part of the market you want to attack.
سوف تريد أيضا أن تعرف أي جزء من السوق تريد الهجوم.
For example, the high end, high quality high margin end
على سبيل المثال، نهاية عالية الجودة، عالية الجودة نهاية الهامش
versus the low end, lower quality, tight margin end.
مقابل نهاية منخفضة، وانخفاض الجودة، نهاية الهامش ضيق.
In consultation with your operations management team,
بالتشاور مع فريق إدارة العمليات،
managerial economists, and your marketing team, your strategy team will
والاقتصاديين الإداريين، وفريق التسويق الخاص بك، سوف
also want to consider whether the company should actually produce the product or
يرغب فريق الإستراتيجية في النظر فيما إذا كان يجب على الشركة إنتاج المنتج بالفعل أو
outsource production and simply distribute.
الاستعانة بمصادر خارجية للإنتاج وتوزيعه ببساطة.
And if your company is going to produce the product,
وإذا كانت شركتك ستنتج المنتج،
just where should the facilities be located?
فأين يجب أن تكون المرافق موجودة؟
Should you produce it locally or perhaps in a state like Tennessee or
يجب أن تنتج محليا أو ربما في ولاية مثل تينيسي أو
Texas with a more business friendly climate?
تكساس مع مناخ أكثر ودية للأعمال التجارية؟
Or should you seek an international location like India, Indonesia or
أو يجب عليك البحث عن موقع دولي مثل الهند أو إندونيسيا أو
Malaysia where wages are cheap but political upheaval is more of a risk.
ماليزيا حيث الأجور رخيصة ولكن الاضطرابات السياسية هي أكثر من خطر.
Let's next suppose that, after reviewing all of the information, you do in
لنفترض بعد ذلك أنه بعد مراجعة جميع المعلومات، فإنك
fact decide that you will produce your own product locally at this point,
تقرر في الواقع أنك ستنتج منتجك الخاص محليًا في هذه المرحلة،
you'll want to discuss with your operations management team
وستريد أن تناقش مع فريق إدارة العمليات
how to design a production process that is most efficient.
كيفية تصميم عملية إنتاج أكثر كفاءة.
This, of course, will entail a detailed examination of your so
وهذا، بطبيعة الحال، سوف ينطوي على فحص مفصل لما
called supply chain.
يسمى سلسلة التوريد.
The chain of various inputs such as energy and
سلسلة من المدخلات المختلفة مثل الطاقة
raw materials in your production process.
والمواد الخام في عملية الإنتاج الخاصة بك.
Now, once you have produced your product, the next step will be to sell it.
الآن، بمجرد أن تنتج منتجك، ستكون الخطوة التالية هي بيعه.
This will be the responsibility of your marketing team.
ستكون هذه مسؤولية فريق التسويق الخاص بك.
It will be the role of this team to
سيكون دور هذا الفريق
figure out the most appropriate distribution channels.
لمعرفة قنوات التوزيع الأنسب.
Should you sell wholesale to big chains like Walmart or Costco, or open your
يجب عليك بيع الجملة إلى سلاسل كبيرة مثل وول مارت أو كوستكو، أو فتح
own line of retail stores or just sell the product Amazon style over the Internet?
خط خاص بك من متاجر التجزئة أو مجرد بيع المنتج نمط الأمازون عبر الإنترنت؟
Your marketing and sales team must also figure out an advertising strategy, and
يجب على فريق التسويق والمبيعات أيضًا معرفة استراتيجية إعلانية،
the most appropriate message around which to build this strategy.
والرسالة الأنسب التي يمكن بناء هذه الاستراتيجية حولها.
Of course with considerable input from your firm's managerial economists
بالطبع مع مدخلات كبيرة من الاقتصاديين الإداريين في شركتك،
the marketing and sales team will also determine a pricing structure.
سيقوم فريق التسويق والمبيعات أيضًا بتحديد هيكل التسعيرة.
Now I am personally convinced that your product will be wildly successful and
الآن أنا مقتنع شخصيا بأن منتجك سيكون ناجحا للغاية
the money will start pouring in.
وسوف يبدأ المال في التدفق.
As it does so, it will be the job of the financial and
و بهذه الطريقة, سيكون من و ظائف
managerial accounting teams to carefully track both cost and revenue flows.
أفرقة المحاسبة المالية و الإدارية تتبع تدفقات التكاليف و الإيرادات بعناية.
Essentially, this team will be your scorekeepers.
أساسا، هذا الفريق سيكون حافظا على النتائج الخاصة بك.
It will be able to tell you whether you are making it or
وسوف تكون قادرة على أن أقول لكم ما إذا كنت تفعل ذلك أو
whether your firm will soon go belly up.
ما إذا كانت شركتك سوف تذهب قريبا البطن.
This team will account for the various cost and revenue streams,
سيقوم هذا الفريق بحساب مختلف التكاليف والإيرادات تيارات،
calculate your profits, earnings to shareholders, and pay your taxes.
وحساب أرباحك، وأرباحك للمساهمين، ودفع الضرائب الخاصة بك.
And importantly, internally use such information to improve decision making.
والأهم من ذلك، استخدام هذه المعلومات داخليا لتحسين صنع القرار.
And how is organization behavior and leadership critical to our story?
وكيف يعتبر سلوك التنظيم والقيادة أمرًا بالغ الأهمية بالنسبة لقصتنا؟
Well in the early stages of the company, you and
حسنا في المراحل المبكرة من الشركة، أنت
your entrepreneurial partners will likely know all or most of the employees.
وشركائك في تنظيم المشاريع من المرجح أن تعرف كل أو معظم الموظفين.
And you together will make most of the decisions.
وأنتم معاً ستتخذون معظم القرارات
And like a lot of entrepreneurs you may manage your company mostly from your gut
ومثل الكثير من رجال الأعمال قد تدير شركتك
rather than in a manner taught in the management textbooks.
في الغالب من أمعائك وليس بطريقة تدرس في الكتب المدرسية للإدارة.
Note, however, that as your company grows and prospers, you will likely notice
لاحظ، مع ذلك، أنه مع نمو شركتك وprospers، ستلاحظ على الأرجح
that not only does it become increasingly difficult to keep track of everyone, but
أنه ليس فقط يصبح من الصعب على نحو متزايد تتبع الجميع، ولكن
also that any flaws in your personal management style will be amplified.
أيضا أن أي عيوب في أسلوب الإدارة الشخصية الخاصة بك سيتم تضخيمها.
Accordingly, once your fledgling company reaches a certain critical mass
وفقا لذلك، بمجرد أن تصل شركتك الوليدة إلى كتلة حرجة معينة
It will become absolutely essential that you pay more and
وسوف يصبح من الضروري للغاية أن تولي المزيد
more attention to how your company is actually organized.
والمزيد من الاهتمام لكيفية تنظيم شركتك في الواقع.
And what incentive structures you have in place to make sure it operates efficiently
وما هي هياكل الحوافز التي لديك للتأكد من أنها تعمل بكفاءة
and to its full potential.
وبإمكاناتها الكاملة.
At such a point, you will come to rely more and
في مثل هذه المرحلة، سوف تأتي إلى الاعتماد أكثر
more on your organizational behavior.
وأكثر على السلوك التنظيمي الخاص بك.
And your human resources management teams to appropriately staff the corporation.
وفرق إدارة الموارد البشرية الخاصة بك لتزويد الشركة بالموظفين بشكل مناسب.
Have procedures in place to ensure best management practices.
وضع إجراءات لضمان أفضل الممارسات الإدارية.
And perhaps most importantly of all create a management culture where morale
وربما الأهم من ذلك كله خلق ثقافة الإدارة حيث الروح المعنوية
is always high, productivity is maximized and efficiency rules.
دائما عالية، وتعظيم الإنتاجية وقواعد الكفاءة.
At this stage in your corporation's development, it will become
في هذه المرحلة من تطوير شركتك، سوف يصبح من
equally important that you become more and more aware of the political and
المهم بنفس القدر أن تصبح أكثر وأكثر وعيا
regulatory environment within which a firm operates.
بالبيئة السياسية والتنظيمية التي تعمل فيها الشركة.
This is where your business and government teams with strut their stuff.
هذا هو المكان الذي عملك وفرق الحكومة مع تبختر الاشياء الخاصة بهم.
Want to locate a new plant in a particular state?
تريد تحديد موقع مصنع جديد في ولاية معينة؟
You may have to lobby the local city council or state legislature for
قد تضطر إلى الضغط على مجلس المدينة المحلي أو الهيئة التشريعية للولاية للحصول
the appropriate permits.
على التصاريح المناسبة.
Make your money primarily from the Internet?
جعل أموالك في المقام الأول من الإنترنت؟
Some states, and even the federal government, may be trying to
بعض الولايات، وحتى الحكومة الاتحادية، قد تحاول
impose new taxes on the Internet that your industry may want to fight.
فرض ضرائب جديدة على الإنترنت قد ترغب صناعتك في محاربتها.
Want a bigger capital investment tax credit that will allow you to build
تريد أكبر ائتمانا ضريبيا استثمارا رأسماليا من شأنها أن تسمح لك لبناء
a new plant locally, and there by help keep jobs in the country?
مصنع جديد محليا، وهناك من خلال مساعدة في الحفاظ على وظائف في البلاد؟
That might be a nice argument that your corporate lobbying team can
قد تكون هذه حجة لطيفة أن فريق الضغط الخاص بالشركة يمكنه
pitch to a congressman or key committee.
أن يتقدم إلى عضو الكونغرس أو لجنة رئيسية.
Of course, throughout this whole process in which your company grows from a small
بالطبع، طوال هذه العملية بأكملها التي تنمو فيها شركتك من
seed in your consciousness to a large cap stock on the New York Stock Exchange,
بذرة صغيرة في وعيك إلى سهم كبير في بورصة نيويورك،
you and all your employees will want to conduct yourselves in a manner consistent
أنت وجميع موظفيك سوف ترغب في التصرف بطريقة تتفق
with both the law and certain ethical cannons.
مع كل من القانون وبعض المدافع الأخلاقية.
However, during this ongoing process of wooing consumers on the one hand and
ومع ذلك، خلال هذه العملية الجارية لاستحواذ المستهلكين من جهة
fighting competitors on the other.
ومحاربة المنافسين من جهة أخرى.
You will soon learn that, at least in some cases, the law will allow you to do
سوف تتعلم قريبا، على الأقل في بعض الحالات، فإن القانون يسمح لك
things that may not In fact, be up to your own ethical standards.
أن تفعل أشياء قد لا تكون في الواقع، على مستوى المعايير الأخلاقية الخاصة بك.
Or you may even be tempted to cross an ethical or
أو قد تميل حتى إلى عبور
legal line to ensure your firm's success.
خط أخلاقي أو قانوني لضمان نجاح شركتك.
In such cases, will you serve your shareholders?
في مثل هذه الحالات، هل ستخدم المساهمين؟
Or your own moral conscious?
أو الوعي الأخلاقي الخاص بك؟
And how, buffeted by these ethical crosswinds,
وكيف
will you determine the right thing to do?
ستحدد الشيء الصحيح الذي ستفعله هذه الرياح المتقاطعة الأخلاقية؟
Hopefully with the help of both your lawyers and
نأمل مع مساعدة من كل من المحامين
other advisors you will figure that out.
والمستشارين الآخرين سوف معرفة ذلك.
And a solid grounding in the concepts and
وهناك أساس متين في مفاهيم
lessons of corporate ethics will surely help.
ودروس أخلاقيات الشركات سيساعد بالتأكيد.
At any rate, you can see from this example how all the various pieces of
على أي حال، يمكنك أن ترى من هذا المثال كيف
the MBA core curriculum fit together to make a profitable enterprise.
تتلاءم جميع الأجزاء المختلفة من المنهاج الأساسي لماجستير إدارة الأعمال مع بعضها البعض لجعل مؤسسة مربحة.
Well you may never be that entrepreneur who starts the whole project to
حسنا قد لا تكون أبدا رجل الأعمال الذي يبدأ المشروع بأكمله في
begin with, this overview will at least give you an idea of how things work.
البداية، هذه النظرة العامة سوف تعطيك على الأقل فكرة عن كيفية عمل الأشياء.
From a career standpoint, one of the worst things you can do in this world is be
من وجهة النظر المهنية، واحدة من أسوأ الأشياء التي يمكنك القيام بها في هذا العالم هو أن تكون
content to be a cog in the machine, and never know how the machine actually works.
راضيا عن أن تكون مسننة في الآلة، ولا تعرف أبدا كيف تعمل الآلة في الواقع.
But here's my last key tip.
ولكن هنا آخر معلومة مفتاحي.
When you're on the job market, if you have a better understanding of how
عندما تكون في سوق العمل، إذا كان لديك فهم أفضل لكيفية
enterprises work, no matter what part of that enterprise you may wind up in you
عمل المؤسسات، بغض النظر عن أي جزء من تلك المؤسسة قد ينتهي بك الأمر في أنك من
are likely to do much better in your job interview,
المرجح أن تفعل أفضل بكثير في مقابلة العمل الخاصة بك،
if you present yourself as someone with a big picture perspective of the enterprise.
إذا قدمت نفسك كشخص لديه منظور صورة كبيرة للمؤسسة.
All right, that's it for part two, when you're ready,
حسنا، هذا هو الجزء الثاني، عندما تكون مستعدا،
move on to part three and our closing remarks.
انتقل إلى الجزء الثالث وملاحظاتنا الختامية.
[MUSIC]
[ موسيقى]